In many occasions, you won't want to end the loop before it's supposed to.
قد تريد في العديد من الأحيان إنهاء حلقة قبل أوانها.
Let's have a look at an example.
لنلقي نظرة إلى مثال.
Imagine you writing a program that controls
تخيل أنك تكتب برنامجاً يتحكم
your smartphone to search for Wi-Fi networks around you.
بهاتفك الذكي للبحث عن شبكات الواي فاي حولك.
You want to retry 10 times and then give up.
تريد المحاولة عشر مرات ثم التوقف.
So we build a loop that starts I from one all the way until 10 and increment by one.
لذا نكتب حلقة تبدأ فيها قيمة "i" بواحد
So this is going to repeat whatever's inside that loop exactly 10 times.
إذن، سيكرر هذا أي تعليمات برمجية موجودة داخل تلك الحلقة عشر مرات بالضبط.
Inside our for loop,
وفي داخل حلقة "for"،
we will be calling this function,
سنستدعي هذه الدالة واسمها "checkWifi".
Imagine that this function actually performs as
تخيل أن هذه الدالة تعمل حقاً
a Wi-Fi search and returns true if it actually found one.
كباحث عن شبكان الإنترنت اللاسلكية، وتُرجع القيمة "true" إذا وجدت شبكة.
So, we're going to assign the return value from
لذا سنسند القيمة الراجعة من هذه الدالة
Which means that if this Boolean is true,
ما يعني أنه إن كان هذا المتغير المنطقي "true"،
then we've successfully found a Wi-Fi network.
نكون عندها قد نجحنا في العثور على شبكة إنترنت لاسلكية،
If it's false, we still haven't found anything, and we keep trying.
وإذا كان "false"، نفذلك يعني أننا لم نجد شيئاً وسنواصل المحاولة.
Right after that, we just add this If condition and check if that variable is true.
نضيف بعد ذلك مباشرة شرط "if" ونتحقق مما إذا كانت قيمة ذلك المتغير هي "true"،
If it is, then we just simply print out Wi-Fi found and that's it.
فإن كانت كذلك، عندها نقوم ببساطة بطباعة "Wi-Fi found"، وهذا كل ما في الأمر.
If it's not true,
وإن لم تكن "true"،
then we keep looping inside our for loop for the 10 times that we want it to.
فسنستمر بالتكرار داخل حلقة "for" لنكمل المرات العشر التي أردناها.
This we'll keep retrying 10 times until it either finds it or not.
سيستمر هذا الكود بالمحاولة عشر مرات إلى أن يجد الشبكة أو لا يجدها.
This looks really perfect,
يبدو هذا مثالياً،
except for one weird scenario where say
فيما عدا سيناريو واحد غريب
Say it iteration number five.
وليكن ذلك في التكرار الخامس.
So, imagine that iteration number five,
تخيل أنه في التكرار رقم خمسة،
our check Wi-Fi happened to return true.
صدف أن أنتجت دالة "checkWifi" القيمة "true".
Updating our variable here to become true.
يتم تحديث هذا المتغير هنا ليصبح "true".
So we step inside our If condition here and we print out Wi-Fi found.
لذا ندخل المستوى الأدنى لعبارة "if" هنا ونطبع "Wifi found".
We end our IF condition,
نقوم بإنهاء عبارة "if" الشرطية،
and we're still inside the loop.
ونكون ما زلنا داخل الحلقة.
So we go back up, we increment I making it six and six is still less than or equal to 10.
لذا نتراجع نزيد قيمة "i" لتصبح ستة، وما تزال ستة أقل أو تساوي عشرة.
So we go back in here again and we check Wi-Fi again,
لذا نعود إلى الداخل مجدداً ونتحقق من الواي فاي مجدداً،
which if we're still in range,
والذي سينتج عنه "true" إذا كنا ما نزال داخل النطاق،
In fact, it will keep printing out Wi-Fi
في الواقع سيستمر في طباعة "Wi-Fi"
for the remaining iterations in our for loop here.
لما تبقى من تكرارات في حلقة "for".
This doesn't seem exactly like what we expected to do.
لا يبدو أن هذا مثل ما توقعناه.
The way I would have imagined it is that once we find a Wi-Fi network,
ما تخيلته أنا هو أنه بمجرد إيجادنا لشبكة إنترنت لاسلكية،
we want to end this search.
فإننا نريد إنهاء البحث.
Luckily, Java offers this keyword called break.
لحسن الحظ، توفر برنامج "Java" كلمة أساسية تُدعى "break".
If we simply add break keyword here,
إن أضفنا ببساطة الكلمة الأساسية "break" هنا،
what we're saying is once we actually find a Wi-Fi and printout Wi-Fi found,
فما نعنيه هو أنه عند إيجادنا للشبكة نتيجة "ًWi-Fi found"
break would actually exit this for loop entirely.
فستقوم "break" بالخروج من الحلقة بأكملها.
So it will not continue looping no matter whether this condition is still true or not.
لذا فهي لن تكمل التنفيذ سواء أكان الشرط ما يزال "true" أم لا.
This is very handy in so many situations that we are going to run into.
هذا مفيد في الكثير من الحالات التي سنواجهها.
In fact, it also works with while loops.
بل إنه يعمل مع حلقات "while" أيضاً.
Let's have a look at an example there.
لنلقي نظرة على مثال هناك.
Imagine that you're playing this game where
تخيل أنك تلعب لعبة
the goal is to roll a dice until you get a six.
هدفها دحرجة حجر نرد حتى حصولك على الرقم ستة،
However, if you get a three then you lose.
ولكنك تخسر إذا حصلت على الرقم ثلاثة.
So we're going to implement a function that keeps rolling a dice until you get a six.
إذن سنكتب دالة تستمر في رمي حجر النرد إلى حين حصولك على ستة.
If you get a six, then you win,
تفوز إن حصلت على الرقم ستة،
but if you get a three, you lose.
لكنك تخسر إن حصلت على الرقم ثلاثة.
Our function would return a Boolean which is true if I won or false if I didn't win.
ستُرجع دالتنا قيمة منطقية تكون "true" إذا فزت، و"false" إن لم أفز.
We'll just call it roll a six.
لنسميها "rollASix"، وهي لن تقبل أي معاملات.
Inside, we'll simply roll the dice using
في داخل الدالة سنقوم ببساطة برمي حجر النرد
the roll dice function and store that into an integer variable called dice,
باستخدام دالة "rollDice" ونخزن الناتج في متغير عدد صحيح اسمه "dice"،
and we'll follow it with our while loop.
وسنتبعه بحلقة "while".
While dice is not equal to six, keep rolling.
طالما "dice" لا تساوي ستة، استمر في رمي حجر النرد.
Perfect. So, this while loop would keep rolling our dice until we eventually get a six.
ممتاز. إذن ستستمر حلقة "while" برمي النرد إلى حين الحصول على رقم ستة بالنهاية.
However, we need to check if the dice ever got a three.
لكن علينا التحقق مما إذا كانت نتيجة أي من رميات حجر النرد هي الرقم ثلاثة.
So we add this if condition,
لذا نضيف عبارة "if" الشرطية هذه،
if dice equals equals three, then we break.
إذا كانت "dice" تساوي ثلاثة، نفذ أمر "break".
Break here means that we're going to break outside this while loop.
تعني "break" أننا سنخرج من حلقة "while" هذه.
We're not going to keep trying,
لن نستمر في المحاولة
we're not going to keep looping inside the while loop.
ولن نستمر في التكرار داخل حلقة "while".
It's over. We've lost.
انتهى الأمر، لقد خسرنا.
However, if you noticed,
لكن لاح أنه سواء حصلنا بالفعل على ستة أو ثلاثة،
We're not going to be able to tell whether we
لن نتمكن من معرفة
actually got a six or a three at that point.
ما إن كنا قد حصلنا على ستة بالفعل أو على ثلاثة عند تلك اللحظة.
So to be able to decide whether we actually won or not,
لذا لنتمكن من تحديد ما إذا كنا قد فزنا أو خسرنا،
we're just going to add another If condition down here.
سنقوم فقط بإضافة شرط "if" أخر هنا بالأسفل.
If the dice is equal to six,
إن كان "dice" يساوي ستة
then we're going to return true,
سنُرجع القيمة "true"،
else, we're going to return false.
وبخلاف ذلك سنُرجع القيمة "false".
So if this while loop kept retrying
إذا استمرت حلقة "while" في إعادة المحاولة
until it eventually got a six and then we got to this phase here,
حتى حصلت في النهاية على رقم ستة، ثم وصلنا إلى هذه المرحلة هنا،
so we just checked that the dice is actually a six, then we return true.
فقد قمنا هنا بالتحقق من أن "dice" تساوي ستة بالفعل، وأرجعنا القيمة "true".
If the dice however happened to have a three in the middle of our retries here,
أما إذا كانت نتيجة رمية النرد هي ثلاثة في إحدى محاولاتنا هنا،
then we're going to break out the loop ending
فسننفذ أمر "break" للخروج من الحلقة لنصل إلى هنا
here and we're going to do this if condition and it's not six.
حيث سنتحقق من شرط "if" هذا، وبما أن "dice" لا تساوي 6،
So it's going to go to the else and it's going to return a false.
ستُحال إلى "else" وستُرجع القيمة "false".
Perfect. So we can see how handy break is even with the while loops.
ممتاز. إذن يمكننا أن نرى فائدة "break" حتى في حلقات "while".
Now, let's have a look at an example where you are going to
لنلقي الآن نظرة إلى مثال حيث ستقوم أنت
use the break keyword to solve a problem.
باستخدام الكلمة الرئيسية "break" لحل مشكلة.